[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Thirty-six]
[第三十六集]
I heard that the Chinese have organized death squads.
我听说华人已经组织了敢死队
Three people for a minister's life.
用三个人换一条公使的命
[Gu Weiju, styled Shaochuan, Ambassador to the United States]
报名者 竟达千人之多
Qingdao is ours!
青岛是我们的
Shandong is ours!
山东是我们的
I really want to go down
我真想下去
and tell them what I think.
跟他们说说我的想法
Don't go out today or tomorrow.
今明两日不得出门
Once you go out, you will be killed.
一旦出门 必遭捕杀
Don't worry. Chief Lu is waiting for a telegram.
不用急 陆总长正在等电报
If it's a signed telegram,
如果是签约电报的话
Rutang,
儒堂
Refuse to sign the Paris Peace Treaty!
拒签巴黎和约
I'll go out with you and make a statement.
我陪你一起出去表态
Refuse to sign the Paris Treaty!
拒签巴黎合约
Okay.
好
Today I'm ready
今天我就准备
to spill my blood to Paris.
把这一腔热血洒给巴黎了
Refuse to sign the Paris Peace Treaty!
拒签巴黎和约
Gentlemen,
各位
it's almost time to sign the treaty.
签约的时间马上就到了
It's evening in Beijing.
北京现在是晚上
The government has already left work.
政府早就下班了
Until now,
到自前为止
I have not received any clear instructions
我没有接到政府
from the government to sign or not to sign.
任何关于签约与否的明确指令
In other words,
也就是说
we have to go our own way.
我们要自行其是了
Zixin, what are your plans?
子欣公 您有什么打算
Go ahead.
您说吧
Shaochuan, I want to hear your opinion first.
少川 我想先听听你的意见
My opinion is simple.
我的意见很简单
Even if the government insists,
即便政府坚持
I will never sign it.
我也决不签字
Rutang,
儒堂
what about you?
你呢
I am no different from Shaochuan.
我与少川并无二致
Good.
好
Gentlemen,
各位
what do you think?
意下如何
Never sign.
决不签字
I drafted two statements.
我起草了两份声明
The first one is for China.
第一份是给国内的
The message is as follows:
电文如下
After detailed review and discussion,
详审商榨
we have no choice but to sign.
不得已不往签字
The second is for the Paris Peace Conference.
第二份是给巴黎和会的
We declare to not sign.
拒签宣言
If you have no objection,
各位如无异议
I'll ask the Secretary General
就请秘书长
to deliver these.
送达了
28 June 1919,
一九一九年六月二十八日
Under the tremendous pressure
在全中国人民
of the continuous mass protests of the entire Chinese people
持续大规模抗争的巨大压力下
and the unprecedented patriotic enthusiasm
在全民族空前高涨的
of the whole nation for national salvation,
爱国救国热情的感召下
the Chinese delegation
中国代表团
finally
最终
refused to sign the humiliating Paris Peace Treaty.
拒绝在屈辱的巴黎和约上签字
This is an important achievement
这是五四爱国运动的
of the May Fourth Patriotic Movement
一个重要成果
a victory in the history of Chinese diplomacy
是自鸦片战争以来
since the Opium War.
中国外交史上的一次胜利
This victory
这个胜利
is the result of the national people's unity and heroic struggle
是全国人民团结一致
against imperialism and the Beiyang government,
与帝国主义和北洋政府
an important symbol
英勇斗争的结果
of the great awakening
中华民族伟大觉醒的
of the Chinese nation.
一个重要标志
Until February 1922,
至一九二二年二月
China and Japan signed
中日两国签订了
the "Treaty on the Settlement of Unsolved Cases in Shandong" and its Appendices
《解决山东悬案的条约》 及其附约
The Shandong problem has been solved to some extent,
山东问题得到一定程度的解决
but Japan continues to maintain considerable power
但日本在山东仍继续保持
in Shandong.
相当大的势力
The time has come.
时机到了
The world's tide is rolling more dramatically.
世界的大潮卷得更急了
The gate of Dongting Lake moved and opened.
洞庭湖的闸门动了 且开了
A mighty new trend of thought
浩浩荡荡的新思潮
has surged on both sides of Xiangjiang River.
业已奔腾 澎湃于湘江两岸了
Follow its life
顺它的生
and die against it
逆它的死
[Mao Zedong, styled Runzhi, Editor-in-chief of the "Xiangjiang Review"]
如何承受它
How to spread it?
如何传播它
How to study it?
如何研究它
How to implement it?
如何施行它
This is the most pressing and most important issue
这是我们全体湘人
for all Xiang (=Hunan) people.
最切最要的大问题
This is the most pressing and most important task
即是湘江出世
for the rise of Xiangjiang.
最切最要的大任务
How to bear it?
如何承受它
How to spread it?
如何传播它
How to study it?
如何研究它
How to implement it?
如何施行它
This is the most pressing and most important issue
这是全体湘人
for all Xiang people.
最切最要的大问题
This is the most pressing and most important task
这是湘江出世
for the rise of Xiangjiang.
最切最要的大任务
Runzhi.
润之
The solidarity rally for Mr. Chen Duxiu
声援陈独秀先生的队伍
is about to leave.
马上就要出发了
Runzhi. Runzhi.
润之 润之
Have all the inaugural issues of the "Xiangjiang Review"
《湘江评论》 的创刊号
come out?
都出来了吗
It's all here.
都在这儿了
Runzhi.
润之啊
Well done.
辛苦你了
These ten days,
这十几天
one person writing,
一个人写稿
one person editing,
一个人编辑
one person typesetting,
一个人排版
one person printing,
一个人印刷
to finish the inaugural issue.
硬把这创刊号赶了出来
It's not easy.
不容易啊
Here. Eat something.
来快吃掉
Here.
来
What is this?
这算什么呀
Mr. Zhongfu,
仲甫先生啊
like a moth to a flame,
能够飞蛾扑火
would rather go to jail
宁愿用坐牢
and wake the world up.
也要让世人惊醒
What is it
我等青年
when I wait for young people to suffer?
吃点苦又算什么呀
You've printed six of them since you came up here.
你这上来就即了六个不怕
Well written.
写得好啊
What is the biggest problem in the world?
世界什么问题最大
Eating is the biggest problem.
吃饭问题最大
What is the strongest power?
什么力量最强
The strength of the people is the strongest.
民众联合的力量最强
What must not be feared?
什么不要怕
Do not fear Heaven.
天不要怕
Do not fear ghosts.
鬼不要怕
Do not fear the dead.
死人不要怕
Do not fear bureaucrats.
官僚不要怕
Do not fear warlords.
军阀不要怕
Do not fear capitalists!
资本家不要怕
Beautiful!
漂亮
Delightful!
痛快
It's all finished.
大功告成
Hurry up.
抓紧时间
Send this inaugural issue to each school
把这个创刊号发给各个学校
and then distribute the presentations.
然后 分头去演讲
Very well.
好好
Hurrah!
好
Fellow citizens,
同胞们
Everyone knows
大家都知道
Mr. Chen Duxiu is a star in Chinese ideological circles.
陈独秀先生是中国思想界的明星
His knowledge of China is always profound.
他对中国的认识常地深刻
China now
现在的中国
is in extreme danger.
可谓是危险极了
In 1919,
一九一九年
young Mao Zedong spent a summer
青年毛泽东在长沙
like fire in Changsha.
度过了一个如火如茶的夏天
He is the editor-in-chief and lead writer
他担任 《湘江评论》 的主编
of the "Xiangjiang Review",
和主要撰稿人
and directed the Hunan Federation of Students
指导湖南学联
to launch the Hunan Federation of Societies
发起湖南各界联合会
to organize a 10-member group to save the nation,
组织救国十人团
to give a speech in the streets of the society,
深入社会 街头发表演讲
and to widely mobilize the people
广泛发动民众
to set off the whole society to rescue Chen Duxiu.
掀起全社会的营救陈独秀活动
He pointed out
他指出
that Mr. Chen Duxiu is a star in Chinese ideological circles,
陈独秀先生是中国思想界的明星
and because of science and democracy
他因为科学和民主
he offended the reactionary authorities.
得罪了反动当局
His arrest will not only not harm him
他的被捕不仅不能损及他的毫未
but will leave a great legacy
反而会留下一个大大的纪念
that will make the new ideas he advocated
使他所倡导的新思潮
more glorious and far-reaching.
越发的光辉远大
Our Tianjin Student Union Newspaper
我们《天津学生联合会报》
After the publication of the inaugural issue,
创刊号出版之后
it has received a lot of attention from all walks of life.
受到社会各界的高度关注
Many readers have written to us
很多读者或来信
or visited us
或登门来访
to ask to hear from us
向我们打听
more news from Mr. Chen Duxiu of Peking University.
北京大学陈独秀先生的消息
[Zhou Enlai, styled Xiangyu, editor-in-chief of the "Tianjin Student Union Newspaper"]
希望我们多发表一些
articles on this subject.
这方面的文章
So rescuing Mr. Chen Duxiu
所以 营救陈独秀先生
will be the focus of our next issue.
将是我们下一期的重点
Everyone needs to work hard
各位要下功夫
to organize more important articles.
多组织几篇重头文章才是
Please.
拜托了
Let's split up.
大家分头工作吧
Professor Chen, bright under the high light.
陈教授 高灯下亮
This one is too small. It hurts my eyes.
这盏太小 伤眼睛
Director Wu, you should call me number 178.
吴总监 你应该叫我一七八号
Professor Chen is very observant of prison rules.
陈教授倒是很守监规呀
Number 178 is what I call you in public.
一七八号那是在公开场合下叫的
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, Professor at Peking University]
今天哪
I'm visiting as a fellow villager.
我是以乡党的身份来探望的
Of course, I have to call you Professor Chen.
那当然得称呼您陈教授了
How are you, Professor Chen?
怎么样 陈教授
Let's have a chat.
咱们俩聊聊吧
Your place, your call.
你的地盘你说了算
Professor Chen is also happy.
陈教授倒也痛快
I had my guys
这是我让我的手下
scrounge this up.
搜罗来的
After you have gone to jail,
你入狱之后的一些报道
you can stay and read some of the reports.
你可以留下来慢慢看
Thanks a lot.
多谢
Thank you, Director Wu.
多谢吴总监关照
It's me who should say thank you.
该说谢谢的是我
How do you say this?
此话怎讲
You'll understand it when you read the newspaper.
你看了报纸就明白了
Professor Chen, it is because of you.
陈教授 正是因为你
I, Wu Bingxiang,
我吴炳湘
have suddenly become a newspaper sensation.
一下子成了报界的红人了
There are only two news figures in the newspaper now.
现在报纸上的新闻人物只有两位
Chen Duxiu is a star-studded man.
陈独秀是众星捧月
I, Wu Bingxiang, have been criticized.
我昊炳湘则被口笔伐
That's what you deserve.
那也是阁下各由自取
Blame no one else.
怨不得别人
There are also brave words.
也有仗义执言的
You talk about this "declaration".
你就说这个 《申报》吧
Let me read it to you.
我来给你念念
Fortunately, police chief Wu Bingxiang
尚幸警察总监吴炳湘
has a novel brain.
脑筋较为新颖
Although threatened by all sides
虽遭各方威肋
and secretly encouraged by the traditionalists,
及守旧派暗中念虑
he has never treated Chen harshly.
然其对陈氏始终毫无苛待
That's true.
这倒也不假
It said Wu Bingxiang didn't treat you badly.
说我吴炳湘对您没有苟待不假
It's not true to say that the traditionalists are secretly encouraging me.
说守旧派暗中惠则不实啊
Look here, there are some.
你看看这儿有啊
Ma Jichang, the leader of Tongcheng School, and Yao Yong
我桐城派首领马其昶 姚永概
issued a statement urging the Metropolitan Police Department
发表的敦促警察厅
to unconditionally release Chen Duxiu.
无条件释放陈独秀的声明
This is very touching to me.
这倒是令我很是感动啊
Whether the people are for or against,
人心向背
Director Wu,
吴总监
I really want to thank you for bringing me in.
我真的要谢谢你把我抓进来
Professor Chen,
陈教授啊
you don't have to get carried away.
你大可不必忘乎所以哪
Don't forget Cai Yuanpei's sentence.
别忘了蔡元培的那句
The story of the roadside children who kill the king's horse.
杀君马者道旁儿的言
Beware of being killed.
当心你被捧杀
I, Chen, know myself.
我陈某有自知之明
This is the inaugural issue of the "Xiangjiang Review".
这份 《湘江评论》 创刊号
This Zedong guy?
这个叫泽东的人哪
Not only did he make you a star in the ideological circle,
不仅把你捧为思想界的明星
he even shouted:
甚至还高呼
long live Mr. Chen's supreme spirit!
我祝陈君至坚至高的精神万岁
This is too much, isn't it?
这也太过了吧
Director Wu,
吴总监
maybe it's someone like Zedong
也许就是像泽东这样的人
who will one day destroy your old world.
将来有一天会冲垮你们的旧世界
Can you destroy the old world?
是否能摧旧世界
It is too early to tell.
结论为时尚早
I want to tell Professor Chen,
我是想告诉陈教授
because of your imprisonment,
因为你的入狱
it really brought great trouble to the government.
确实给政府带来了极大的麻烦
Now almost the whole of China is moving.
现在几乎整个中国都动起来了
It is unprecedented.
可谓前所未有
It's an unexpected thing?
意料中的事啊
But this is not a good thing for Professor Chen.
可这对陈教授并非是好事啊
Now everyone knows,
现在大家都知道
you are the number one political enemy of the government.
你是政府的头号政敌
Many people are yelling at me to hand you over.
许多人着让我把你交出去
Once you get out of the police station,
一旦你走出了警察厅
you can imagine the consequences.
后果可想而知啊
It's nothing more than a broken head.
无非就是断头流而嘛
I have no regrets
亦余心之所善兮
even after nine deaths.
虽九死其犹未悔
However, Professor Chen,
不过陈教授
now you're at the end of your rope.
你现在可是山穷水尽了
If you can have some cooperation with my police department,
若能与我警察厅有一些合作的话
maybe you can have a bright future.
或许还可以柳暗花明
Maybe.
或许
Stop.
打住
If you say again I will be scolded.
你要再说我可要骂人了
Do you think I, Chen Duxiu,
你觉得我陈独秀是那种
am the kind of person
对自己的信仰
who can make compromises on his beliefs?
可以做出妥协的人吗
As expected.
果然不出所料
Professor Chen is really a man of character.
陈教授果然是性情中人哪
So you can stick to your faith.
好 你坚持你的信仰
I stick to my duty.
我恪守我的职责
Let's see.
咱们走着看
Don't bother to see me out.
不送
Listen not to the rain beating against the trees.
莫听穿林打叶声
Why don't you slowly walk and chant with ease?
何妨吟啸且徐行
Better than saddled horse, I choose sandals and cane,
竹杖芒鞋轻胜马
Oh, I would fain,
谁怕
In a straw cloak, spend my life in mist and rain.
一裳烟雨任平生
It's all you want to see
都是你想看的
Good.
好
My wife knows me.
知我者 夫人也
Although I'm trapped in prison these days,
这段日子我虽然身陷唇
my heart is more free to fly.
心却更加自由放飞
There are many new ideas.
有很多新想法
Suffering from having nowhere to pour out.
苦于无处倾泄
It's worse than not being able to shit.
简直比拉不出屎来还难受
Watch your mouth. The children are here.
你说话注意点 孩子们都在呢
Dad.
爸爸
You must be bored by yourself every day.
您每天一个人 一定很无聊吧
Let Yingying talk with you.
就让英英陪陪您 说说话吧
Okay, Zeimei.
好子美
This is good.
这个好
In the right context,
合情合景
we are both in the cage.
我们两个都在笼子里
We share the same illness, we share the same room.
同室相依
Zhongfu, don't say such discouraging things.
仲甫 别说这么丧气的话
Now all the people in China are rescuing you.
现在全中国的人都在营救你
You will be released from prison soon.
你很快就会出狱的
That's right, Uncle Chen.
就是陈伯伯
My father wrote that
我爸爸来信说
Shanghai established the National Federation of Students.
上海成立全国学联
Someone put forward a slogan
有人提出口号
that said until Chen Duxiu gets out of prison, they will never resume classes.
说陈独秀不出狱 决不复课
I see.
我知道
I feel that the the core of the action now
我感觉现在整个运动中心
has been transferred from Beijing to Shanghai.
已经从北京转移到上海了
The working class has stepped onto the stage of history.
工人阶级已经登上了历史的舞台
This is a great event.
这可是一件了不起的大事件
You are in the cell.
您这在牢房里面
You're not isolated from the news.
消息也并不闭塞呀
I don't listen to things outside the window all day.
我整天两耳不闻窗外事
Just concentrating on reading, studying and thinking.
一心只是读书学习思考
Of course I'm not isolated.
当然不闭塞了
What are you thinking about, sir?
先生 您都在思考些什么呀
Mostly thinking about two problems:
最集中的是两个问题
Marxism and the Russian Revolution.
马克思主义和俄国革命
So these problems
那这是一个问题
are all about socialism.
者是社会主义
Not exactly the same thing.
不完全是一回事
One is the original.
一个是原生态
One is the latest achievement.
一个是最新成果
One is theory and the other is practice.
一个是理论一个是实践
The two complement each other.
两者相得益彰
Yannian, I still suggest that you and Qiaonian
延年 我还是建议你和乔年
read Marx's works.
去读一读马克思的著作
Especially on 6 April,
尤其是四月六日
that issue of the "Weekly Review"
那刊的《每周评论》
published the second chapter of the "Communist Manifesto".
刊登了 《共产党宣言》 的第二章
It can help you
可以帮助你们
learn more about Marxism
更多地了解马克思主义
I almost forgot if you didn't tell me.
您不说我差点忘了
Mr. Shizhi asked me to bring to you
这是适之先生让我带给您的
the latest two issues of the "Weekly Review".
《每周评论》 最新的两期
Isn't Mr. Dazhao absent?
大钊先生不是不在吗
Mr. Shizhi took over directly.
适之先生就直接接手了
Is this the "Weekly Review"?
是《每周评论》吗
Is this the "Weekly Review"
这是我陈独秀创办的
founded by Chen Duxiu?
《每周评论》吗
Why are you so angry?
怎么了 发这么大的火
This is not the "Weekly Review".
这不是《每周评论》
This is a special issue of Dewey's research.
这是杜威的研究专
This Hu Shizhi,
这个胡适之
not only did he cancel
他不仅取消了
the combat articles and sharp commentaries
我和守常特别重视的
reflecting the political struggle
反映政治斗争的战斗性文章
to which Shouchang and I attached special importance,
和尖锐的评论
he also withdrew the review of major domestic events
他还撤销了国内大事述评
and international affairs.
和国际大事述评
Two columns that readers pay special attention to.
两个读者特别关注的专栏
Look at the eight pages of these two issues.
你们看看 这两期全篇八个版面
All published are Dewey's research records.
刊登的全都是杜威研究录
What's the noise?
什么吵
Be quiet!
安静点
Go!
去
Get me Hu Shi!
把胡适之给我叫来
Explain it to me face to face!
当面给我解释
Professor Chen,
陈教授
look who I brought you.
你瞧我把谁给你带来了
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
You're suffering.
受苦了
Professor Chen, what's wrong with you?
陈教授 您这是怎么了
So far away from people.
如此拒人于千里之外
This is not the style of a mentor.
这可不是导师的风范啊
Director Wu,
吴总监
I wrote an inscription especially for you.
我呢专门为你写了一幅字
Please take it.
请笑纳
To thank you for taking care of me.
以感谢你对我的关照
Spring leaves Shenpu,
春申浦上离歌急
Yangtze River is long in spring.
扬子江头春色长
Take good care of it,
此去凭君珍重看
and see the mulberry plants in sea.
海中又见几株桑
This was before Su Manshu went to Japan.
这是苏曼殊去日本之前
The poem I gave him in Anqing.
在安庆我送给他的诗
There is no special meaning.
没有什么特别的含义
By convention, there should be couplets.
按常规 应该有楹首
The cut
拦腰
and the bend.
和压角
But here it is.
但是在这儿嘛
Just follow your rules.
就按照你们的规矩
Here.
来
Professor Chen, you really have a personality.
陈教授 你真是有个性啊
Can you write poems on this?
能把诗写在这个上面
There is no big piece of paper.
没有大张的纸了
Do not do evil,
诸恶莫作
practice good.
众善奉行
Take care of yourself.
凭君珍重
I must treasure it well.
在下一定好好珍藏
This poem has a profound meaning.
此诗寓意颇深哪
Professor Hu,
胡教授
today, I've touched your glory.
我今天算是沾了你的光了
To have such a treasure.
能得如此墨宝
You guys talk, I'll leave you alone.
你们聊吧手 我就不打扰了
Do not do evil,
诸恶莫作
practice good.
凭君珍重
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
Yingying with snowy claws.
雪泥鸿爪的英英
This little thing is always with you.
这小东西一直在陪着你
It's better than me.
它比我强
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
A picture of my ancestors looking forward to the Hundred Days' Reform.
这是我儿祖望百日的照片
Take a look.
你看一下
You weren't there during the Hundred Days' Reform.
百日的时候你不在
I didn't invite a banquet.
我没有请宴席
Shizhi,
适之
I'm sorry I spoiled your fun.
对不起 我扫你兴了
Brother Zhongfu,
仲甫兄
I really came to make amends to you.
我真是来给你赔罪的
Shizhi,
适之
you really have to tell me about it.
你真的得给我讲讲
This is why?
这到底是为什么
After I took over the "Weekly Review",
我接手《每周评论》 以后
Wu Bingxiang came to me.
吴炳湘就来找过我
He repeatedly warned me to talk less about current affairs
一再地警告我说要少谈时事
and talk less about politics.
少谈政治
Otherwise, it will be banned immediately
否则的话就立即取缔
and I'll add guilt to you.
而且还要给你加罪
I have no choice.
我是没有办法
I can only take this approach.
我只能采取了这种
The "Weekly Review"
《每周评论》
No politics, no current affairs.
不谈政治 不谈时事
What is the "Weekly Review"?
算什么 《每周评论》
It's not that we don't talk about current affairs or politics.
不是不谈时事 不谈政治
Instead, they talk about important current affairs and specific politics.
而是大谈时事 专谈政治
Brother Zhongfu, don't you think
仲甫兄难道你认为
Professor Dewey's coming to China is a current event?
杜威教授他来华不是时事吗
that Professor Dewey's special issue is politics?
杜威教授他的专刊不是政治吗
that Professor Dewey's experimentalism
杜威教授他的实验主义
of governing the people are all in your favor?
民治思想也都是你赞成的
This is politics.
这就是政治呀
What you said is not unreasonable.
你说的倒也不无道理
But I think
不过我认为
the top priority now
现在的当务之急
is to borrow the east wind of the May Fourth Movement
是要借五四运动的东风
and well publicize it
大力宣传
to encourage the people
鼓动民众起来
to fundamentally transform our society
从根本上改造我们这个社会
to find a scientific way to save the country and the people.
寻找一条救国救民的科学道路
The Two magazines.
两个杂志
The main idea of "New Youth" is enlightenment.
《新青年》主旨思想启蒙
The "Weekly Review" guides the mass movement.
《每周评论》 引导群众运动
The two magazines complement each other.
两个杂志相得益彰
They have to play their roles.
都要起到这个作用才行啊
Finding your way is really important.
寻路确实重要
The key is to pay attention to some scientific methods.
关键还要讲究一些科学的方法
I thought that now we
我以为现在的我们
must study more questions
必须要多研究一些问题
and talk less about socialism.
少谈一些主义
Brother Zhongfu, talking is wrong for the country
仲甫兄 清谈误国
This truth must be told more.
这个道理一定要多讲啊
Shizhi, your point of view is worth squeezing.
适之 你这个观点值得商榨
Without good scientific guidance,
没有好的科学主义指导
how can we study the problem well?
怎么能研究好问题
You're asking for nothing.
你这是舍本求未
This view of yours
你这种观点
will be criticized by Shouchang.
一定会遭到守常的批判
Right?
对吗
You're right.
你说得没错
Now I don't know why
现在我也不知道为什么
Shouchang's and my ideas
守常和我在思想上的分歧
are getting more and more divergent.
是越来越大了
He is now fully focused
他现在全心
on the violent revolution in Soviet Russia,
扑在了苏俄的暴力革命上面
moving towards Bolshevism.
动辑就是布尔什维克主义
It's dangerous.
这很危险
Shizhi.
适之
Three of us.
我们三个人
Shouchang is a fan of Russia.
守常是俄国派
You are a fan of the United States.
你是美国派
I used to be a fan of France.
我之前是法国派
But now I'm
不过我现在
more and more inclined to Shouchang's Russian camp.
越来越倾向于守常的俄国派
The question you asked just now,
你刚才提出的问
I advocate for a debate.
我主张开展论
Okay, I'll take the lead.
好 我来挑这个头
But now Shouchang and I must be opposites.
不过现在我和守常肯定是对立的
Brother Zhongfu, which side are you on?
仲甫兄 您站哪一头
Let me write you an inscription, too.
我也给你写幅字吧
Liu Mei, go and ask Yannian to have dinner.
柳眉 你去喊延年吃饭吧
Right away.
马上好了
Okay.
行
Yannian, time to eat.
吃饭了
I won't eat. You can eat first.
我就不吃了 你们先吃吧
Where are you packing for?
你这收拾东西去哪儿啊
I'll find Mr. Dazhao
我去找大钊先生
and see if he can save Chen Duxiu.
看他有没有办法救陈独秀
Then where are you going to find them?
那你去哪儿找他们呀
He's at Hanwengong Temple.
他在韩文公祠
Why didn't you tell me earlier?
你怎么不早跟我说呢
I'll pack my bags, too.
我也收拾行李去
Why? Come here.
干吗去 你过来
What's going on?
怎么了
I'm not going to take you there.
我没打算带你去
What do you mean?
什么意思啊
I'll do this alone.
这个事我一个人去就行了
You'd better listen and go back to Shanghai.
你还是听话 快回上海去
My family is in this situation.
我家现在这个情况
It's not good for you either
对你也没有好
and it may involve your family.
而且可能会连累到你的家人
What's the matter with you two?
你们俩怎么回事啊
You haven't come to dinner for so long.
这么久还不来吃饭
What's going on?
怎么了
I'm fine, auntie.
我没事姨妈
What happened to her?
她怎么了
Where are you going?
你这是要去哪儿啊
I'll find Mr. Dazhao.
我去找大钊先生
See if he can save Chen Duxiu.
看他有没有办法能救陈独秀
Auntie, I'm not eating.
姨妈 饭我就不吃了
All the meals are served for you.
饭都给你盛好了
No, I won't eat.
不吃我不吃了
Brother.
老哥
When the wheat is harvested,
等麦子下来了
[Li Dazhao, styled Shouchang, Director of Peking University Library]
就能吃上白面馒头了吧
After contributions and taxes,
又是捐又是税的
there isn't much wheat left.
这麦子也剩不了几个了
I am reluctant to eat at ordinary times.
平常的时候还舍不得吃
I save it for festivals.
留着逢年过节再吃
Usually eaten at home,
平时家里吃的
or sweet potato or corn.
还是红薯 棒子
This is not enough to eat.
这还不够吃呢
There are not many shops here.
这不 多开点地
Can you plant more and count more?
能种多些算多些吧
What if it's not enough to eat?
那不够吃怎么办
Usually eat less.
平常少吃点
Eat dry food during the farming season and eat thin food during the day.
农忙时吃干的 平时吃稀的
If you can't eat enough, go out and borrow some.
实在不够吃 就出去借点
Go begging when you can't borrow it.
借不到的时候 就去要饭吃呗
Brother.
老哥
Have you ever thought about it?
你们想过没有
Our harvest is so good,
咱收成这么好
yet the day is still so hard
吕子过得还这么苦
and you have to go out and beg for food.
还得出去要饭去
What is the truth of this?
这是个什么道理
Life.
命呗
Life as a horse and cow.
当牛做马的命啊
No way out.
没办法
Can't compete with your types.
比不了你们这些
A teacher who knows how to read.
识文断字的教书先生
It's not our destiny to be cattle and horses.
当牛做马不是咱的命
Life, huh?
命啊
We have to decide for ourselves.
得咱自己个儿定啊
Ride!
驾
Uncle Li.
李大叔
Someone wants to see you.
有人找你
Who?
谁啊
Go!
走
Yannian.
延年
Sir.
先生
Hello, sir.
先生好
There won't be any bad news, will there?
不会有什么坏消息吧
Is your dad okay?
你爸爸没事吧
He's fine.
没事
The police department just sent out a message
警察厅刚刚发出了消息
and said to hold a press briefing
说要开一个记者通气会
to make public his situation in prison.
向社会公布一下他在狱中的情况
That's good.
那就好
Then why are you here looking for me?
那你跑这儿找我来干什么
I want you to do something,
我是想请您想想办法
see if you can get him out early.
看能不能让他早点出来
You two are quite interesting.
你们爷俩还挺有意思啊
Arguing when we meet.
见面就吵
But what about the critical moment?
可是关键时刻呢
You're pretty good with him.
你还挺店着他
Not caring about him.
不是关心他
I'm worried about me, auntie.
我是担心我姨妈
She was so anxious that she couldn't sleep all night.
她这一晚上的着急得睡不着觉
You boy.
你小子
Just keep your mouth shut.
就是嘴硬
Come and take off your clothes.
来把衣服脱了
Help me chop wood.
帮我劈柴
Okay.
行
Actually, about your father,
其实你父亲的事啊
you have nothing to worry about.
你完全不用担心
He is far-sighted, but he has no near worries.
他是虽有远虑 但是并无近忧
What do you mean?
什么意思
Your father's case is important to them.
你父亲的案子对于他们上面来说
It's actually quite tricky.
其实是挺棘手的
There should be two opinions now.
现在 应该有两种意见
The first opinion
第一种意见
is that of the generals of the Anfu Club,
就是以曹汝霖 王怀庆为首的
led by Cao Rulin and Wang Huaiqing, who had been removed from their posts.
安福系那些被免职了的将领
They will kill brother Zhongfu, and then do it quickly.
他们必欲置仲甫兄于死地而后快
Another opinion
另外一种意见
is that of the new Premier Gong Xinzhan.
就是新任总理龚心湛
He advocated the release of your father to reassure the people.
他主张释放你父亲 以安民心
What about President Xu Shichang's wishful thinking?
那么总统徐世昌的如意算盘呢
Trying to use your father as a pawn
是想把你父亲当作一颗棋子
to negotiate with the Southern government
好和南方政府谈判
Understand?
明白了吧
The tripartite forces are involved in a wide range.
三方势力 牵扯甚广
If your father is outside,
如果你父亲在外头
then you will probably be involved
那么多半会被卷入到
in the political struggle.
政治斗争之中
I guess I'll have to skin it if I die.
我估计不死也得扒层皮
But as it happens, he is inside now.
但是巧了 他现在在里头
Instead, we avoided this disaster.
反而避开了这次灾难
That is to say
那也就是说
it's wise not to do anything
现在什么都不做
right now.
反倒是最明智的
Not doing nothing,
不是什么都不做
but not doing it openly.
而是不能明着做
Actually the Students' Federation
其实学联
has been secretly guiding the direction of public opinion.
一直都在暗中引导舆论的走向
As long as people's mood reaches a critical point,
只要民众的情绪到达一个临界点
everything will be solved.
一切问题就都解决了
Then I'll be clear when you say so.
那您这么说我就明自了
Now that you're here,
你既然来了
stay here for a few more days.
就在这儿多住几天
Let's do farm work during the day
白天呢咱们干干农活
and read books together in the evening.
晚上一块读读书
Just in time, Zhao Shiyan, Zhongxie,
正好赵世炎啊 仲解呀
Yi Qunxian will come in a couple of days.
易群先哪 过两天也会来
It's only
只不过
that the life here is a bit poor.
就是这儿的生活条差了点
Sir.
先生
I would love to have that.
这我就求之不得了
Your conditions here are really not bad.
您这儿的条件真不算差
I've lived in far worse places than here.
比这儿差得多的我都住过
Sir, you have prepared so many dishes.
先生 您准备这么多菜
Can you eat by yourself?
一个人吃得了吗
These dishes are all sent by fellow villagers.
这些菜都是老乡送的
They are working in the ground now.
他们现在在地里头干活呢
Let's eat together at night.
晚上大伙一块吃饭啊
All right.
好
Journalists!
各位记者
I have just finished reporting to you
刚才我把陈独秀先生被抓的经过
the circumstances of Mr. Chen Duxiu's arrest
以及他在看守所的情况
and his situation in the detention center.
向大家已经汇报完毕了
I would like to answer three questions from you.
下边 我愿意回答诸位的三个问题
Please.
请吧
Mr. Chen Duxiu is already held at the police station
陈独秀先生已经在警察厅
for a month.
关押了一个月
May I ask Director Wu, will he be convicted?
请问吴总监他会被定罪吗
What will be the crime?
会定什么罪
How many years will it take?
要判多少年呢
Will Mr. Chen Duxiu be convicted?
陈独秀先生会不会定罪
What crime? How many years?
定什么罪 判几年
It is still under investigation.
还在立案侦查当中
I can only answer this question so much.
这个问题我只能回答这么多了
Please.
请
Just introduced information
刚才介绍说
that Mr. Chen Duxiu received preferential treatment in prison.
陈独秀先生在狱中受到了优待
Excuse me, Director Wu,
请问吴总监
what specific preferential treatment did Mr. Chen receive?
陈先生受到了哪些具体的优待呢
Mr. Chen is a celebrity.
陈先生是社会名流
What he committed involved many factors.
他犯的事涉及到诸多因素
Therefore, he received special preferential treatment.
因此受到了特殊的优待
Like his food.
比如他的伙食
It refers to the standards of the first-class superintendent.
是参照一级警司的标准
Solitary confinement
单独监禁嘛麻
means, that within a certain range,
就是说在一定的范围当中
he is free
自由活动
to read books and newspapers and write.
看书 看报写作
Friends and relatives and his colleagues
亲朋好友以及他的同事
can visit him.
可以来探视
I can tell you responsibly,
我可以负责任地告诉大家
this month
这一个月
Mr. Chen Duxiu gained four pounds.
陈独秀先生足足胖了四斤
Director Wu,
吴总监
the media in Beijing are eager to form a group.
京城媒介迫切地希望能够组团
or go to the police station alone
或者单独前往警察厅
to interview Mr. Chen Duxiu,
去采访陈独秀先生
or allow us to publish some
或者充许我们发表一些
words written by Professor Chen in prison.
陈教授在狱中写的文字
Director Wu, please grant permission.
请昊总监恩准
During the investigation period,
立案侦查期间
no interview.
不得采访
Do not publish articles.
不得发表文章
What the media wants
媒体所要的报道
should be in accordance with
应一律按照
the notification from the Metropolitan Police Department.
京师警察厅的通报为准
I have already answered three questions.
三个问题我已经回答完了
Dismissed.
散会
Director Wu! Director Wu!
吴总监
We haven't finished asking yet.
还没问完呢
[Hanwengong Temple, Wufengshan, Changli, Hebei]
一封朝奏九重天
And I'm banished eight thousand miles away.
夕贬潮阳路八千
To undo the misdeeds I would have given aid.
欲为圣明除事
Dare I have spared myself with powers in decay?
肯将衰朽惜残年
The Ridge veiled in barred clouds, my home can't be seen;
云横秦岭家何在
The Blue Pass covered by snow, my horse won’t go forward.
雪拥蓝关马不前
This is Mr. Han Yu's letter saying that he was demoted to Chaozhou.
这是韩愈先生上书言政被贬潮州
A famous poem written on the way out of Beijing.
在出京路上写下的著名诗篇
What about home?
国内呢
There are several ancestral halls in memory of Mr. Han Yu.
纪念韩愈先生的祠堂有好几处
One is in Mengzhou, Henan.
一处是在河南的孟州
That's Mr. Han Yu's hometown.
那是韩愈先生的家乡
Another place is Chaozhou, Guangdong.
再一处 是在广东潮州
Mr. Han Yu was there once.
韩愈先生曾经在那儿
Lived for a while.
住了一段时间
Another place is our Changli, Hebei.
还有一处 就是我们河北昌黎了
Actually, Hebei's Changli and Mr. Han Yu
其实河北昌黎和韩愈先生
don't have much to do with each other.
没有什么太大关系
It's just the same name as his birthplace.
只不过是和他的出生地同名
So in the Ming Dynasty,
所以在明朝的时候
someone has built two Hanwengong temples successively.
先后有人建了两座韩文公祠
Located in Changli County,
一座在昌黎县城
here is another one right here.
还有一座 就是在这儿
Mr. Shouchang,
守常先生
everyone says you are a master of criticizing Confucianism.
大家都说 您是批儒大师
How do you live here,
您怎么会住在这个
in the ancestral hall of respecting Confucian scholars?
尊儒文人的祠堂里
Who said I was a master of Confucianism?
谁说我是批儒大师
Isn't that ridiculous?
这不太荒唐了吗
Aren't you and Mr. Chen Duxiu, Mr. Hu Shi
您和陈独秀先生 胡适先生
all critics of Confucius?
韩文
The criticism of Confucius is political respect for Confucius.
文
I and brother Zhongfu
我和仲甫兄
are very respectful of Confucian culture.
是非常尊重儒学文化的
Mr. Zhongfu's has a deep study
仲甫先生对于儒学的传统
of the Confucian tradition.
有很深的研究
The reason why I live here
我之所以住在这儿
is also to express my respect
也是为了表达
to the ancient literary master
我对于古代文学大家
Mr. Han Yu.
韩愈先生的尊敬
I reread recently
最近 我又重读了
several articles by Mr. Han Yu
韩愈先生几篇文章
and benefited a lot from them.
受益匪浅啊
Mr. Han Yu had a difficult life.
韩愈先生一生坎
For the poem and the essay, it directly points out the bad governance of the time.
为诗为文 直指时整
[He Mengxiong, Visiting student at Peking University]
发言真率 慷慨陈词
The thought of his article
其文章之思想
can be said that it is glorious and ancient.
可以说是光耀干古
Students, isn't the purpose of our struggle today
同学们手 我们今日之抗争
to eradicate the bad governance of China?
不也是为了给中国铲除整政吗
So everyone must
所以大家一定要
know this clearly.
认识清楚了这一点
Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生
Some time ago,
前些时候
when Uncle Chen was editing
陈伯伯在编辑
the manuscript of "New Youth"
《新青年》 文稿时
This is the content.
就这个内容啊
I wrote a letter to Mr. Zhang Tuzhao
给章土钊先生写过一封信
about this viewpoint of yours.
谈的就是您这个观点
I remember when he read it to us,
我记得当时他还念给我们听呢
said it would be published
说要在下一期
in the next issue of "New Youth".
《新青年》上发表
Is this letter still there?
这封信现在还在吗
When the police ransacked the house, they found it.
警察抄家的时候给搜走了
Remind your father to get it back then.
提醒你爸爸 到时候把它要回来
Come on, students.
来同学们
Let's go in and have a look.
我们进去看看
Come on, come on, students.
来来来同学们
Let's take a look back.
咱们往后边来看看
This is my humble room.
来这个就是我的陋室了
The room is humble, but my heart is noble.
斯是陋室 惟吾德馨
And here,
还有这儿
this will be our little classroom from now on.
这个 以后就是咱的小课堂了
Is it all right?
好不好
It's good!
好好好
Qunxian.
群先
Wash the fruit for everyone.
把水果给大伙洗洗
Give everyone some.
给大伙分分
Okay.
好
The fruit here is particularly good.
这儿的水果特别好
Qiaonian.
乔年
Go there and get some stools and set them up.
去那儿搬几个凳子 摆过来
Okay.
好
Zhongxie.
仲
Tell us all about the situation.
给我们大伙说说形势吧
Okay.
好
Mr. Cai called a few days ago
前几天蔡先生致电
the Peking University Student Affairs Office
北大学生干事会
to give up resignation
表示放弃辞职
and wait until his stomach trouble is cured,
等到他胃病好了以后啊
only then can he go back to school.
就可以回学校了
Okay.
好
Mr. Zhongfu's case,
仲甫先生的案子
according to Mr. Zhang Shizhao,
据章士钊先生所说
the police department didn't find
警察厅并未查到
any evidence of his breaking the law.
任何他犯法的证据
So in a few days,
所以再过几天
Mr. Zhongfu will be released from prison.
仲甫先生就能出狱了
This is good news.
这是个好消息
Overall speaking,
总体来讲
after the Paris Peace Treaty was refused,
巴黎和约拒签之后
the situation in the whole country has gradually stabilized.
全国的局势就逐渐稳定下来了
A few days ago,
前几天
All-China Federation of Students has decided to end the strike.
全国学联已经决定结束罢课
After the summer vacation, classes will officially resume.
等到暑假之后就正式复课
Peace talks between the North and South governments,
南北两个政府的和谈
although it has been two months,
虽然已经过去两个月了
it seems that the prospect is not very optimistic.
不过好像前景并不太乐观
But the most important thing is
不过最关键的是
the May Fourth Movement
五四运动
has awakened the patriotic enthusiasm of the whole country.
唤醒了全国民众的爱国热情
From the initial student movement,
从最初的学生运动
it has gradually evolved into the whole country
逐渐演变成为全国
to even the patriotic national salvation movement of all Chinese.
乃至全体华人的爱国救亡运动
Guess what western critics say?
你们猜西方评论怎么说
What did they said?
怎么说
The lions of East Asia have awakened.
东亚雄狮觉醒了
Great!
好
Students
同学们
I have Changli specialty wine here.
我这儿有昌黎的特产葡萄酒
To the May Fourth Movement,
让我们为了五四运动
let's drink!
干一杯
Okay.
好
Sir.
先生
I don't drink.
我就不喝酒了
Substitute tea for wine.
以茶代酒
Okay.
好
Me too. Me too.
我也是 我也是
Here's to the May Fourth Movement.
为了五四运动 干杯
Cheers.
干杯
Everybody sit down.
大伙坐
Students.
同学们
We are all witnesses of the May Fourth Movement.
咱们大家都是五四运动的亲历者
The May Fourth Movement was great.
五四运动是伟大的
Then I want to ask my classmates.
那么我想问问同学们
What is the greatness of the May 4th Movement?
五四运动究竞伟大在什么地方
Large scale, and large number of people,
规模大 人数多
then all walks of life took part.
然后 各行各业都参加了
Qunxian is right.
群先说得没错